You have a bunch of animation data that are unstructured data and you want to be able to
use those to generate a new animation specifically along a path or something like that.
Hi, I'm Jerome and today we'll be looking at one of my favorite papers of all time,
motion graphs, a paper from 2002. What I would do is that I will import my libraries as usual
and then I will import my character and I will load one animation and then we could see that
animation to show you what it is. It's basically a character walking along and doing a bunch of
stuff inside of that animation but that animation is 7000 frame long which is a bit big for this
kind of paper that was written a long time ago that was probably not dealing with that much of
data and to speed up a little the process I would actually reduce that animation and I will do it
as if it was small clips instead of having one big animation. So what I do is that I only keep
a few ranges so what I would do is that I will only keep three pieces of the animation and I will
reuse that as being my animation so I would just convert the animation itself and now
it's basically the same. I have the beginning of the animation and then it would do a few
walk and then jump in a different spot there. So that's one clip, the next clip and then does the
same here, a bunch of walking and then it will walk, walk, then jump. So it's basically three
different clips but I'm still packing them inside of one animation which will make my life
easier inside of the notebook, the paper itself would actually work with several clips of one
big animation. It's up to you on how you want to do it. Then, motion graphs. Basically, the idea
of motion graphs is to have your animations and then build a graph out of it. And to build that
graph, there will be a few steps to go through before being able to reach the graph status.
And basically, if you go through the motion graph constructions,
the first thing is to find the best candidate to make a graph out of it.
So imagine you have two animations and you want to figure out from which frame inside of a first
animation you could reach another frame and that would give you a transition that is smooth and
doesn't pop. And so basically what you have to do is figure out inside of all your frames of
animation, find the one that are matching so you could do the transitions. And there are several
ways to detect those candidates. You could do it by checking the orientations of the bones
and all that kind of stuff. But then, you know, quaternions can be tricky finding just the thing
that rotations on the small rotation on the hips can have a lot of big impact while a small
rotation on the hands has nearly no impact. So what I've decided to do is that instead of
of looking at orientations itself,
they said that what we see is actually a mesh.
So what is the best solution to match
is to make sure that visually the mesh will be matching.
So you can test mesh with mesh
because there will be a lot of vertices and that kind of stuff.
So what they will do is that they will build a point cloud.
And a point cloud is a lighter version of the mesh itself.
itself. So what I would do is that I would generate my point cloud with the
same kind of idea. So basically I have a bunch of points attached to each bone.
So you see for the hips I have five points here that are attached for the
right up leg. I have four bones, right leg, four bones, and four points. Sorry.
So you get all those points. And to make my life easier at the end, also instead
of remembering those cloud points and then recomputing their positions every time, I will
actually generate a point cloud animation. So that's what I did here. I get a cloud animation so
that I get all my frames, all the points cannot count and XYZ. So I have a bunch of points floating
in space. And so that's my animation now that we could see what we have here is exactly this.
we have the character walking and we get all the points that represent the point
clouds attached to it as separate animations but synchronized. So I have
the point clouds, I can start to, I know how to build the point clouds, I can
start to look at the paper on how to compute the stuff. So those point clouds
will be used to actually compute the distance between two frames. So you want to calculate the
distance between frame AI and BJ. And instead of considering just the point clouds of frame AI
and BJ, what they would do is that they know that we want to do a transition between AI and BJ.
So, we would take a window of frames to do the point clouds.
So the point clouds itself would not be frame AI, it will be frame AI up to frame AI plus
10, something like that.
And frame BJ will be BJ minus 10 up to BJ.
So, what Salo allows us to do is to make sure that not only the position will be the same,
But then the velocities of those points will be the same because they will be at the same
position along several frames.
So I'm not matching only one position, I'm matching the position, the velocities and
even the accelerations if the windows is big enough.
And so that's what we can do here.
See, instead of having one, I go a bit further here, instead of having one point closed,
I can actually have all the frame in front.
that basically be, if I try to match frame A, that's frame A, and I want to match frame B,
that frame B, it's all the point clouds in the back that represent one point cloud in front and
one point cloud in front, one point cloud in back. So that's what we'll be comparing together
to compute the distance. So my transition will be smooth. Now to compute the distance between the
Those two point clouds we have to remember that they are in world space. So my characters is moving along
inside of the
animation and we want to make sure that when we compute the distance we compute the best distance possible
if we did realign both characters together and
So instead of just computing the distance itself what you do is actually you compute the minimized
distance. So instead of computing just the distance, you compute the distance of PI.
So PI is one point inside of my first point cloud. And P prime I is that corresponding
point inside of the second point cloud, except that you could transform. So that's what the
t is it's a transformation of the second point clouds and you could rotate theta and move x and z.
So basically meaning that if I have one point cloud and I have a second point cloud I can
with here for instance I can rotate it and I can move it on the same spot and then I'm trying to
find the best stuff that gives me the minimal error possible and that gives me the best alignment
and a minimal error. Luckily we don't have to actually run that minimized function
because there is a closed form solution to that transform issues and that's the formula for the
closed form solution so that's the angle and x and z offsets and basically what I would do is
is have that functions as is.
So it's really see the sum of the weights
divided by the sum and all that kind of stuff.
Give me the angle x and z and I can return angle x and z.
And we could use now that Poincare alignment
inside of our animations directly to see what they do.
And so what I have is, for instance,
I would move this character.
So I get character in the back is my A frame, let's say character in front is my B frame.
You could see that I'm computing the cloud alignments every single time.
So of course, this guy now always stays more or less where the other guy is and you get
the error, the amount of errors that each point clouds is giving me.
So even when the error is really big, the alignment is not too bad.
And then I get the T that set me to display what the transition would be if I was trying
to do a transition between that frame A and that frame B.
With a really big error like this, you could see that the transition is quite ugly.
Basically you could see that the feet are just sliding.
It makes no sense at all.
So I'm just basically sliding.
if I find an animation that has a frame that has a smaller error somewhere, can I find something?
I'm sorry, 3,000, I'm not too bad. Let's say 3,000 here, and I try to do that with transitions.
Now I get transitions that actually make a step, and so that transition is more natural
than the other one. So at least we can compute the alignments, we can compute the distance,
and then we could see that the transitions, if we were to take a transition at that time,
it would work. So let's give us the distance functions and now what we need to do is to
make sure that we can actually select when we want to do that transitions. So and to do this,
what we will do is that we will compute, basically this, we will compute the distance
between every frame with every frames and it will give us the error for every possible frames
and what I would do for this is actually I would instead of running my function that I wrote here
which is in NumPy I will actually run that functions rewrite that functions using the warp
library and the warp library is an Nvidia library that's allow you to write
Python code that is compiled into CUDA and runs on your GPU because my
animations is 1000 frames so I actually have to do 1000 multiply by 1000 tests
that's a lot of different tests that's a lot of alignments and all that kind of
stuff so I will run that on the GPU that will be faster so I will compile this
So it's the same functions basically exactly the same code written a bit
differently to run on the GPU. Now compute the alignments and then the
functions that compute the distance basically aligns the two point clouds
stores the angle x and z values so I will be able to reuse it and then I
compute the distance and I store the distance and now I can run this here so
it takes a bit of time because it compiles the CUDA code and I will launch that on my GPU and
runs for every points inside of the system and I will come back to you when it's done.
Now it has computed the all the distance functions and you could see basically that
mapping between every frames with every frames. Of course the line right in the middle there
is the absolute best zero error because it's basically said I want to do a
transition with the animations that it should be playing anyway because it's
basically frame frame 200 with frame 200 is the same is the same frame you're
mapping but then all the other one all the different blacks area are potential
transition you could take between different different animation so I
So I should be able to take a transition from frame 225 with the frame 50.
That's the kind of stuff this map shows us.
And the white rear is actually the three different animations I have.
It was three clips back to back, so that white rear is actually transitioning from one clip
to another.
something it's out of bounds you shouldn't be playing any animations right there in the middle
but that gives us an idea of all the arrows and then basically it's not enough to know that all
those are really good candidates we don't want to basically have a graph that says I can take
a transition from this frame this frame this frame this frame this frame and having a really big
graph that goes nuts with tons of connections. What we want to do is what they did here,
what they're mapping is different, white is the best, black is the worst, and for me it's the
difference. But then what you try to do is to find the local minima. So the green dot represents
the place where along all the frames around here, I'm the one that is the lowest error. So you
you should pick me and nothing next to me
because if I'm the best case,
I would be the best case around me.
So it's finding the local minima
and then I would do the same.
I will compute the local minima
and again, I will do it inside of
a CUDA kernel, just checking if for every frames,
is all the frames around me worse and better than me
they're all worth and me I'm a good candidate except if my error is too big anyway or if I'm
on that diagonal area I don't want to be able to do transitions between myself so I run it on the
GPU and I have the same thing except that if we go and zoom a little you could see all those
yellow dots basically means they are local minima that are good enough to take a transition.
So all of those would be transition points now inside of my graph.
And to build the graph, what I would do is having a node inside of the graph, which has
a node ID, it knows the start frame in which the node starts, its end frames when it stops,
And all the edges you can take at the end, so when you reach the end, that's all the
possible edge I can take, all the transitions I can take.
And an edge basically has a start frame, end frame, does it blend or not, we'll come
into it soon.
An angle and X and Z, which were all the point clouds were aligned when we did that transition.
And basically, when I'm starting this, what I do is that I start with a list of nodes,
list of edges, and the frame mappings allow me to know basically which frame belongs to
which node.
So at least I have something that maps the length of the animations.
I can say, hey, frame 25 in my animations, which node do you belong to?
And that kind of stuff.
So that's what the frame mapping allows me to do.
And I'm building the graph starting with three nodes which are the three different clips
and without any edge between them, it's just three nodes and that's it.
And then to build the graph, you take every local minima you found inside of the animation
and the way I'm doing it is you can represent your graph several ways.
The choice I made is to say that a node always play its entire animations up to the end and
only at the end can you take an edge to reach another node.
I don't have edges that start in the middle of nodes and that kind of stuff, it's just
at the end of the node you need to take an edge.
So if a local minima says I'm leaving that node right in the middle of the node, the
The first thing I do is, here, I'm actually splitting the node in two different nodes,
and I have the first node that points towards the second one, saying that is a transition
without any blend, because basically it's just back-to-back animations.
And there is the second edges from that that goes from the end of the first node up to
the actual frames I want to go in with the blending informations and angle and transforms
and all kind of stuff and then you get all the edges and that kind of stuff and then building
the graph you get this graph here and then you could see nodes so that's the entire graph all the
nodes I have here with all their edges and all kind of stuff so lots lots of nodes that were
building the graph. Now the issue we have when you do this when build a graph
like this one what happened at some point is that you have this kind of
graph and for instance if you were trying to traverse this graph to build
animation and all of those if you reach the node number five you will be stuck
there is no ways to get back inside of the animation and so the node five is
and logo, it has to be removed basically from the graph, otherwise you might get stuck inside
of your graph. And the way that they're pruning the graph basically is to compute the strongly
connected components and you take the biggest one, the largest one, and that becomes the subgraph
you keep. So in this case, you know, the biggest strongly connected graph is just this one, two,
three, six, seven, eight. Everything else is discarded because it's not part of the biggest
strongly graph. This one would be another strongly connected graph, but it's smaller
than the other one. So keep on that, remove everything else. And that's how they prune the
graph. It's a bit more complex because they also support the fact that you might have different
type of animations inside of your graph. You might have, you know, all locomotions and then all
crouching locomotions and all kind of stuff. So what you would do is that you will compute a
strongly connected graph per type inside of those and you will keep the strongly connected,
each of the strongly connected one for each style. In my case I only have one so it would be easier.
I can only compute the main one and that would be enough. And to prune that graph to compute the
strongly connected one, they use the Tarjan algorithm, which is what I've done here. It's
the pure implementation of the Tarjan algorithm. I would not spend time explaining this one in
And in this video, I might do another video talking about algorithms and covering this
more in depth.
But you can find a bunch of videos on internet anyway.
Basically what it gives me, that's all the strongly connected graph.
It's well connected in our case here, so basically this one is the big graph I can use.
And all of those are graphs that are just representing one node that are completely out of access.
So basically we want to keep all those nodes and then we can discard all those.
And I will do it as the paper is doing it.
So you basically traverse every edges and if an edge reach outside of the biggest subgraph,
delete that edge. Once you've done that for all the edges, you go through all the nodes
that basically have no edges that leave them. And delete all those nodes. And then what
I'm doing is I'm remapping all the nodes, basically saying that, you know, the frame
the node three and zero were gone. I didn't like having IDs and dangling IDs. So basically
I'm remapping all my IDs now to go back again from zero up to 500 something.
That's just the remapping. So what you have is that the number of edges I had before,
so I deleted 50 edges and I've deleted four nodes. That's it.
And once you have your graph like this, you could actually try to start to extract motion. So
So you could do a walk through your graph
and generate, what I have here, the transitions here,
the transitions itself.
So you could walk through the animations
and through the graphs and append animations back to back
and make the transitions between different animations.
And that's what this function started me to do.
Basically, I have the append no blend.
So, you know, I've split a node in two.
So I might want to actually be able to play back those nodes
back to back inside of my animation again.
So that's what the app on NoBlend does.
It takes the frame inside of my source animations.
The frame I'm starting, the frame I'm ending,
and the generated animations.
So the generated animation is the buffer
which I'm building the animation that I'm outputting. And basically the only thing it does is
imagine my character was walking and doing this and then I said that I want to append an animation
that is from here. It takes that that animations realign it back at the end of my animation and
stick it there and then keep going. So that's what it does. It realigns the clip and then
And then you get the appen blend, which is the one that actually do a real transitions
between two frames.
Bit more complex because it has to know the current frame I was playing at the end of
my nodes and where I'm starting my transitions
and where I'm ending the clip I'm adding.
And why do I need to do this?
It's because, remember, I've said that I split nodes into
as soon as I had the transition,
which means now that if my character is here,
the first thing I need to do is to stick back
the next few frames after so I can do the transition
and then I can bring the new animation,
put it in the same spot,
and so the transition would happen.
So it's a bit complex, so that's what I do here.
The first thing is, if I was at frame 50,
I take frame 51 to frame 60, for instance,
and bring it back here, realign it.
Then I take animation B, so if my animation A is here,
here, my animation B, it was there. I take my animation B and I make it do the same offset
that this one did. So my A moved here, so my B moved there at the same time, do that with the B.
And now that I have actually moved everything together, I can use the phi X and Z that was
compute it by the cloud alignments to realign this on the same spot. So bring A on the same spot,
bring B relative and B on the right spot thanks to the cloud alignments and then do the actual
blend transitions. So blend a few frames and when you did that you get the blend and then
after happened the end of the animations without the blend.
And what I do in the blend is that I compute this not as a linear blending, I do it with
is in is out, which is what they explained here, except that their mathematics are a
bit weird and I don't know why they go a parameterized between minus one and K instead of zero
and one but basically what I do is that I will be using this one which is the same formula that
the one we've seen inside of the footscate cleanup. It's an easy knees out function that's
allowed me to get a value that goes between zero and one linearly and give me a zero and one with
a easy knees out which is that minus two x cube plus three x squared and that's the one I'm using
here so I do an easy and easy blending and then I get the up and edge which makes my life easier
take an edge find the length of every note it has to do make sure that it's a blend or not a blend
call the right stuff and up and that toward the animation so as soon as we have this I can do for
instance a completely random walk inside of the animation which is what I do here I have a max
frame of 1000 and see as long as I haven't reached at least 900 frames, I'm just adding randomly an
edge to the to the animation and that's it. And we could see what happens if you do this.
You basically have this character that walks and do random stuff between different animations.
What we see all the different colors is when which node is in, what the frame is playing,
and the red and blue are the skeleton from and to transitions and the transition itself.
And see, it goes and randomly pick any animation. But it's fairly smooth because we
would basically force it to to find smooth transitions between the two.
That's the extract motion I want a bit further.
So searching for motions, because we haven't searched, we did actually work randomly,
and they say is useless to work randomly inside your graph.
I agree is probably a bit useless, might be useful if you try to train neural network, but
in most of the case is useless to do random work.
What you want to do is to be able to actually do a proper search
through that graph.
You do need to be able to give a purpose, a goal,
and a cost function, say, how quickly you're
getting to that goal and how fast you get to that goal.
And so the way they've decided to do it
is, there is the naive solutions as I said, I used to go depth first search and search every
possible graph work you could do and pick the best one. Unfortunately that graph is fairly big
and so as soon as you try to do this you will probably kill your computer trying to find the
best solutions or wait for several thousand years. So there is a lot of different algorithms that
have been studied along the years to solve these kind of issues. And the one they've picked in
this case is to just do a branch and bound algorithm. Again, I will not go too much in
detail with the branch and bound because I will probably do another video about it.
but basically what the branch and bound does is just to make sure that when you
start a search every single time you you you want to keep going further into your
search you checking if you haven't found a path that was better than that one
before so basically you keep track of the best path you found and if you if you
find something that is better than the one we had you store that one and as
soon as inside of your search you detect that it will be worth you stop and so
the way they're doing it here is that every time you happen every time you
happen an edge through your path you compute the error and that becomes the
error the the the amount of error or the cost of that path and then you compare that every time with
the best path you found and you stop as soon as you add an edge that we say but if I'm adding
this edge now it will be worse than everything you found you stop the entire branch search so
that's what the algorithm here is doing so I get the path I get the last node the amount of error
the number of frames that this path is covering and then the list of edges. I don't need anything
else to be able to rebuild an animation than the list of edges because an edge will give me a node.
I need to play up to the end of that node and then take that and the next edge and so on. So
I think the list of edges is enough for me to compute a path. And then the search algorithm is
is just, as I said, the branch and bound algorithm.
And one stuff I could compute
with the branch and bound here is basically saying,
okay, I have a stop function.
Say if you reach that, you actually found the solution.
And the reason why I would stop the search is that
if you reach the node that has a node ID 200,
It means that you are in the goal I was looking for.
And when I open the functions,
the only thing I do is I'm adding an edge, of course.
And then when I'm adding the edge,
I just compute the path and the amount of error
is just a number of frame.
So basically, the only thing I'm trying to
force the search here to do
is to find the shortest animation
that will take me from one frame to another frame
inside of my animations.
So I will probably start at node zero.
So if I'm starting at node zeroes
and I'm trying to reach node 200
and I'm asking to find the path,
and he said he found the solutions
and he did it in 26 frames.
I can generate the animation out of it
and I can display this animation.
And basically, that was the solution
we found to go from node zero, which is a frame 300.
And you can say 300, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 145.
So it did jump back in time, and then it reached the solutions.
So, and you could test other,
let's try to reach node 500.
It did find a solution in 60 frames,
that's a bit bigger.
And so from node zero up to that pose,
that was the shortest path you could find.
So pension bonds allow you to search through your graph
depending of an input, cost functions,
a goal and cost functions, let's say.
Now, again, searching for a mission like this,
they said deciding what to ask for,
said asking for the shortest frames like this
might not be useful, again,
depending on what you try to do with it.
What they are interesting in their case
is trying to make the character walk along a certain path.
And to do this, I would actually do what they do also.
The first thing that I will generate a path
that I want to create.
So I would do it with Kubic Bezier.
I will have videos explaining all the mathematics
between all those functions that will arrive soon.
But basically that's what I have here.
Is the path I want my character to follow so I want him to start here walk along this path and
Reach that point there and I will compute
All the curve distance and and trajectory so I can I can do this and what I would do is that
The cost functions and and the the stop would be a bit different
I will execute this because it's not really optimized
We take time to compute so
Let it compute while I'm talking
So what is the stop function now? It's actually saying that if the path my character has taken is
As long as the path I wanted him to walk along
You've reached your goal. So that's the stop functions. That's the reason why I wanted to stop
And then when I happen an edge, that's where stuff is really not optimized because it was is just for a testing purpose more than actually
making something running fast
What I do is that every time an edge I build the entire animation from that
path and I use that animations to compute the errors between what my
character is walking along so basically I take every frame of my animation that
has been generated, take the distance that the character is walking, and walk at the
same speed along the curve I want him to follow, and I compute the distance between every point
and assume that error as being the entire amount of error for the entire arc.
And so basically that's what I'm doing here, computing the entire errors, total distance
covered and that kind of stuff and I create that new path.
Now even the branch and bound in this case would actually be extremely slow because
there is a lot of solutions to walk along that long curve.
So what they did in the paper and what I've done here is to say, I will not try to generate
that path in one go as impossible. I will try to find a suboptimal solution. And to do this,
I'm basically doing this. You would say you could look for the best path, but only for,
in this case, 34 frames. And you'll find the best solution to make sure that the character
walk along those along the path for those among the frames and then I will go back a little
and I will restart from that point and I will redo a search of 34 frames from there and then I
will go back a little and then redo a search and so on and so on so that's how you get a sub-optimal
because you might have not found the best ways of walking along the path but at least every small
steps is computable and you could try to reach it. You could see that's what it's doing here.
It said that at the first time it did not find the solution. Of course it has only
two frames of animations. So it didn't find and then eventually it did reach the end goal
at some point and then we could see how it did it. So I can generate the animations and we could
display this animation here. And we can see how he managed to walk along. I have absolutely
zero constraint on the speed. I'm not asking him to do anything except walking. It is not
even has any real intent to say you cannot stop. The only thing that I'm doing is that
I'm putting the goal a little in front of him. So the errors keep accumulating if you
refused to walk, let's say. So there is other cost functions that could be more complex.
We could try to force him to make sure that it doesn't go through stops and all that kind of stuff.
It was just here as a test to see if we could generate the path through an animations this way.
I haven't implemented the entire paper. As you can see, the feet are sliding. I didn't add the
the foot lock that I would need to actually put
in the animation data at the first step to say
that's the transition, you need to make sure
that your feet are not sliding or that kind of stuff.
I've skipped that part because really what I was interested
in was the motion graph.
I hope you enjoyed this motion graphs video
as much as I love this paper.
It's really a paper that starts a lot of different papers
at the end.
There is a bunch of papers talking about
how to improve the graph generations, the amount of transitions it can take.
There is papers that use this to to say how can we use this as a runtime in video games,
that kind of stuff. So there is a lot of papers at the end. And it's really the paper I always
come back to as soon as try to design something. Usually I come back to this one as a ground ID
before starting to do anything more complex. So I hope you enjoyed it and see you next time.